Hi, dear students. I hope
you're all doing well.
And let's begin our next lecture.
And from that book, which we started from, so we're skipping chapter three, because chapter
three is about
language and communication.
I hope this subject
can be familiar to you and straightforward.
The only important point from the chapter can be the
team about the use of language to manipulate.
So if you guys are interested in this topic, maybe you can search from internet and learn about
the ways how people use language to manipulate, whether it's been politics or in business
or in different spheres.
Okay. So today we are starting chapter four, which is about
knowledge, evidence, and errors in thinking.
And let's start with the following case about Peter Raley from the USA.
So in 1973, Peter
Raley, he was about
18 year old, a young guy, senior high school student.
And at that time,
when he returned from a church, he discovered
that his mother
was brutally murdered in their home, in the bedroom.
Okay. And he immediately called the police.
And even though there was no any real
evidence, maybe such as blood in his hand or some other kind of points
related to this guy, police suspected Peter as someone responsible for the murder.
And the reason for this suspicion was that the people around
and also maybe police also knew that his mother was apparently a difficult woman with a special
kind of character that kind of had the delight in belittling people,
including his son, Peter.
And when he was taken for interrogation,
Peter waived his right to an
authority and thinking if he told the truth, he would soon be released.
And however, during interrogation
by a rotating team of policemen, they repeatedly suggested or kind of pushed
him
that maybe he went into rage, right?
Maybe he was really kind of
unhappy with his mother and maybe eventually he murdered his mother.
Okay. However, when he denied this charge, And they kept urging him
to dig deeper into his unconscious and into his memory so that maybe he can find out
more information.
And about 16 hours later,
since the start of these interrogations, And
Rayleigh, this Peter Rayleigh, he started to begin to remember some of the details of the event,
supposedly like he was murdering his mother.
And several hours later,
he was very exhausted and finally he was confused.
And he was also confused and he made a confession that he murdered his mother.
Okay, so even though he later came to doubt his role in the murder and his confession was
the most compelling piece of evidence in the criminal court and eventually he was sentenced
to certain years of jail.
Okay, so however within two years, I mean because his relatives and his friends and the people
around him since they knew about this guy and they didn't believe the story and they kept
for they kept questioning the interrogation process and investigation and looking for some
evidence and eventually he was released after two years from the prison because the court
was presented another evidence suggesting that during the time of murder he was in a different
place okay
and
However, the policeman, the police department still kept believing that he was the murderer.
However, the real murderers were not found
until then. This case illustrates how social expectations and the
leading questions can alter the person's beliefs and memories.
Therefore, good critical thinking skills require that we evaluate evidence thoroughly and be
aware of social and cognitive errors in our thinking
to effectively evaluate any given situation and avoid jumping to particular conclusion.
So based on this case
in our mind, let's begin our topic in more detail.
And here are the themes or subtopics which we'll be discussing today.
first of all about the human knowledge and its limitations
and then we'll talk about evaluating evidence and then about the cognitive and perceptual errors
in thinking and finally about social errors and biases.
Okay guys, just a second.
Let me check if
If everything is working well, I hope the sound is also well.
Okay, let me continue. So let's begin with the first subtopic, which is about human knowledge
and its limitations. So what do we understand by knowledge?
Knowledge is kind of an information, right?
or maybe some experience that we had, right?
Maybe some event that we believe to be true and for which we have justification or kind of
a proof, right?
To kind of,
to show to people, right?
That based on this evidence, we believe that this information is true and therefore we have
this knowledge about, right?
And understanding how we acquire knowledge as well as having an awareness of the limitations
of the human understanding.
are essential in logical reasoning.
And there are certain kinds of points in regards to this, first of all, about rationalism.
And some of you may have heard about this kind of philosophy, right?
And our views of ourselves and the world around us are shaped by our understanding of the nature
of truth and the ultimate source of knowledge.
And the rationalists, they claim that the most human knowledge comes through reason.
And the Greek philosopher Plato believed that there is an unchanging truth we can know through
reason, and that most of us confuse truth with worldly appearance.
So, however, there's also a different kind of people, believers,
who we can call empiricists, right?
They reject the rationalist claim that it's through reason that we discern truth.
So empiricists instead claim that we discover truth primarily through our physical senses,
right? And it can also be called as empirical evidence, right?
So we know that this kind of empirical evidence has become a kind of a main tool of scientists,
right? So scientists, they believe or they kind of
they have trust on the empirical evidence, right?
They need to kind of find out from the real world, right?
Maybe based on certain data, based on certain kind of maybe interviews, right?
Or maybe field data, or maybe based on some
viewings, right? And they will kind of come to certain conclusion.
So, however, like
right after these two kind of
points, there are also
another kind of people, right, which were kind of motivated by another philosopher
from Germany, more recent philosopher, right, Kant, who rejected both rationalism and
empiricism, okay? He argued that how we experience reality is not simply a matter of pure reason
or using physical senses,
but also depends on the structure of our minds,
like computers, which are designed to accept and process particular kinds of inputs from the
outside world. Our brains also must have the correct hardware to accept and make sense of incoming
data. Okay.
And
most psychologists and neurologists of our time also kind of share this belief of Kant.
Okay. About this point that we do not see reality directly.
as it is, but that instead our mind or brain provides structure and rules
for processing incoming information.
In other words, we're kind of, we
interpret the incoming information through our lenses, right?
So all of us may have our own kind of
past experiences, our worldview or our philosophy.
In other words, we can call it as a lens, right?
Or worldview. So we kind of take through this kind of
worldview all the incoming information, right?
We kind of process through this kind of filter and then we kind of make sense of the incoming
information or make sense of the world and so on.
And let's talk about evaluating
evidence.
And what do we understand by telling
evidence? So what is evidence?
And by evidence, we mean something that tends to prove or disprove a particular view, right?
So if we have certain point or claim to make, and in order to prove this claim, we need to
bring some evidence, right?
This can be maybe some data or maybe some research.
or maybe someone else claim, right?
So based on this, providing this evidence or this example, right, real life examples, we can
kind of prove, or we can try to prove our main
kind of point of view, for example,
right? And evidence can come from many different
sources, right? And sometimes they can be reliable or not reliable.
Let's talk about one of the sources, which is about the direct experience.
Effective critical thinking requires that we will be willing to check the accuracy of our own
experiences. As we noted earlier, our brains organize and interpret rather than
directly record the sensory input, the sensory experience.
As a result, a direct sensory experience may not be always reliable.
So even though we may remember major events as though they were yesterday, these memories are
not as stable as scientists once thought.
And for example, there was a study done four years right after the 1986
Challenger disaster, and they found out that many of the witnesses had dramatically altered
their memories of the shuttle disaster, even to the point of seeing things that had never happened.
And for example, like we may have also
seen, right?
There is a certain kind of a game that was kind of popular in the social media, right?
Where let's say the teacher or someone kind of
tells something to one person or maybe shows a kind of certain movements to some person.
And then that person needs to pass it to the other person, right?
And then there's a change, right?
And by the end, maybe it will come differently, right?
At the end of the day, the whole story may kind of become altered, right?
And another point is about false memory syndrome.
And
we are so suggestible that we may go beyond
inadvertently altering memories and on to vividly recall events that never happened.
And this kind of a syndrome can be called as a false memory syndrome.
Psychologists have found that after only three sessions in which there are repeated suggestions
about non-existent childhood events, such as being lost in the mall, for example, right?
When you were maybe five or six years old, right?
Or maybe a spilling of some juice, for example, right?
on some guests during certain events, for example, right?
After that,
about one quarter of the people, they start to recall similar events from their childhood.
And what's more, there's little connection between their confidence in their memory and truth
of their memory. And therefore, by
being more attentive and analyzing events as they happen, And by being alert to
inconsistencies in our memories, we are less likely to be taken in my false or distorted
memories. And the next point is about hearsay.
And we should be also skeptical of what other people tell us, especially if it's hearsay
evidence or comments taken out of context.
Okay. And by hearsay, we mean the evidence that is heard
by one person and then repeat it to another person.
And so on until you hear it is notoriously unreliable, right?
It's kind of maybe gossip, right?
You can say it's a gossip.
And
there is also a
term of
anecdotal evidence, right?
You may have heard about it, which is based on the personal
testimonies So, which is also
not reliable because of the problem of inaccurate memory, as well as the human tendency
to kind of manipulate or
exaggerate or distort what we experience to fit our kind of
expectations, right?
For example, many people
in the USA, like based on the book, they may have reported seeing these flying objects, right,
from the space, maybe
some kind of shuttles, for example, right, by
aliens, right? So, however, despite many claims, right, and the sincerity of their beliefs,
right, so it's still considered as anecdotal evidence because there is no any kind of real
evidence
evidence or data for this.
And let's talk about experts and credibility.
And one of the most credible sources of information
comes from the professionals or the
experts of a certain fields, right?
And when we're turning to an expert, it's important that we find someone who is knowledgeable
in the particular field
of the
kind of the
question we're discussing, for example, right?
And when we use the testimony of a different person who is expert in a different field, so
we're kind of committing some kind of a fallacy of appeal to inappropriate authority, right?
So which we will talk about it in the later chapters.
And
here comes some of the points, right?
Some of the kind of credentials
that we need to be looking
in experts when we want to give the microphone or the kind of turn to the kind of points of
experts, right? First of all, we need to look at their education or training, right?
That they should be from a reputable institution, right?
And secondly, experience in making judgments in their fields.
And thirdly, reputation among peers as an expert in the field, right?
So by reputation, we do not mean
from the YouTube, for example, right?
Or maybe by having certain blogs or telegram channels or by having a certain number of
followers, right? By reputation, I mean the kind of
reputation
in their field, right? A kind of recognition by their peers, for example.
And lastly,
accomplishments in the field, such as academic papers, maybe right.
And some kind of research, right.
Whether they really conducted a certain research or certain kind of, uh, knowledge seeking
activities in their field.
And here comes a question.
Can we always trust, uh, this type of, uh,
uh, people, right. With this knowledge and education, can they always be right?
Can you guys post this video and think about it?
Okay guys, yes, sometimes this type of experts may also make mistakes, right?
And their
claims or their testimonies, they are not foolproof and experts may disagree, in which case
we'll have to reserve a judgment
or look to others in the field, right?
And furthermore, sometimes experts can be biased also, right?
Particularly those who are being paid by some special interest groups, maybe by some businesses,
or maybe by government. If the research is funded
by certain organizations, we should be careful about whether they're
really
honest or not. For example, here the book is a good example that it has
been long assumed that the milk and dairy products help maintain strong bonds in
people, right? Especially in the
older people. However, this claim has not been supported by scientific research and instead
it has been mainly promoted by groups that financially depend on the sale of dairy products.
And let's talk about evaluating
evidence, okay?
So,
when we are debating or when we're kind of receiving information, right, certain type of claim
and certain type of
reasons, right, or certain type of data behind this claim, we need to check, right, whether
this evidence
is a kind of
reality is real, right? Whether the data is not distorted, for example, right?
And we should do some type of
analysis, right? And credible evidence is consistent
with other relevant evidence.
So in addition, the more evidence there is to support a claim, the more reasonable is to accept
that claim. Okay. So sometimes we do not have access to credible evidence
for a claim. in such cases, so we should look for contradictory evidence, right?
So there may be such situations.
And when we're evaluating the evidence, we should also need to watch out for the
confirmation bias, right?
And by confirmation bias, we mean the tendency to look only for evidence that confirms
only our assumptions of the world, right?
Only our views of the reality, right?
And to resist evidence, that contradicts them.
So this inclination is so strong that we may even disregard or reinterpret evidence
that runs contrary to our cherished beliefs, for example.
And we know that sometimes politicians, right, or maybe some marketers, they may try to
manipulate with a similar type of evidences, for example, right?
And they may kind of cherry pick the evidence and presenting only the reports and listening
to evidence that support their previous beliefs, for example.
And confirmation bias may also take the form of more
rigorously scrutinizing contrary evidence than that which supports our position.
And the next point
in order to
evaluate the validity of the
evidence is to look for research resources, right?
We
live today because in a time of
information age, right?
We're kind of, we are bombarded with the zillions of data and news and information, right?
And in such a case, So the
important kind of a skill is to find out
what information or what source is reliable and what type of information or claims or the sources
are not reliable, right?
And when we are using evidence from the media, especially from the mass media, we need to consider
the sources and their slant if any.
In addition, some writing such as maybe novels, poetry and even editorials is not intended
to be taken as factual, right?
Because there may be certain kind of cases in real life, right?
Where maybe we have read a certain novel, right?
Or we have watched some kind of historical movie based on real life, maybe
historical event, right?
Maybe about
Amir Timur, for example, right?
Or maybe some Genghis Khan or maybe some kind of European
historical figures, right?
So even though kind of the movie is kind of based on some historical evidence or historical
figures, right? So we know that Amir Timur, he was a real person.
And we may know that he was born in certain place and we know that he fought against certain
people, but still, since this is a kind of a movie or novel, we know that there will be a
kind of a, some distortion of information or some type of manipulation of data, or maybe just
a kind of a, some type
of.
Creativity of the makers of the novels and movies.
Right.
So similarly, therefore, I mean, we should not take such a kind of such type of resources for
the kind of trustful evidence, okay?
And like good scientists, good critical thinkers, they need to spend a lot of time researching
claims and collecting information before coming to certain conclusion, right?
Or before coming to certain claim.
As you begin your research, you should try to set up an interview, first of all, with someone
who is an
expert or professional in that field.
Maybe he can be or she can be a faculty member, or maybe someone from outside, for example.
An expert can provide you with information as well as point you to reputable publications.
When
interviewing that expert, don't just rely on your memory.
take some notes. Okay, repeat what you think you heard if you're unsure.
Okay. And also, you can also ask help from the libraries, for example, right?
They may also direct you to certain kind of books or resources, for example.
And from the internet, we know nowadays everything is in internet, right?
Maybe you don't have to go to library.
In internet, we have these online dictionaries, online libraries, or maybe
encyclopedias, right? So however, we know that Wikipedia also
may not be really reliable because people usually they kind of write it.
So even though regardless of this still in the end of the Wikipedia page, you know that there
are sources, right? So we can directly go to the sources in order to kind of come to a belief.
I mean, if this article or the
kind of page in the Wikipedia is a claiming the truth or they're just making up themselves,
right?
And moreover, there are also scholarly journals, right?
Which contains articles that have been reviewed by the fellow experts in the field, right?
And there are also government documents, right?
And also there are websites by the government or there are websites of international
organizations, right? So they can be the most reliable sources of information, right?
And then there will be some secondary or third party resources, which kind of make their
judgment or claims based on that data, right?
Maybe the government published statistics, right?
We have statistics office in Uzbekistan every year, they publish a kind of a data, right?
Certain data about the number of population and number of maybe people by gender, by age groups,
right? So we can, we should directly go to the source, right?
order to see what's true and not true.
Or maybe like, as I said, there may be some international organizations, right?
Like United Nations or maybe
some other sub organizations of the United Nations, right?
Like UNESCO maybe, right?
Or maybe some economies organizations, right?
Like
WTO World Trade Organization, right?
And many others, right?
So usually they also kind of publish some type of
research and other reports, right?
So we can directly go to them.
Oh, like I said, we can also for the
empirical research, right?
For the research from the real field, if you really want to know what the scientists are saying,
we should go maybe to Google Scholar, right?
So you can type scholar.google.com.
So if you type there, so it can give some kind of a list of papers, And however,
there is a problem because this Google Scholar is open source.
Still, there are some researchers who are kind of chasing the numbers and the quantities.
So they may try to manipulate.
So still, even though we find some
empirical articles, we need to evaluate also that paper, the journal is coming from, right?
Whether it's a reputable journal, and there's also a source called SchemaGo, right?
Which kind of evaluates the journal ranking.
So hopefully, maybe later on, if we have a chance, we can kind of talk about this.
I think we have a
chapter specifically about science.
Yes, hopefully later on in the end of the first part of our semester, we'll have a chance to
talk about research
more.
Let's talk about our next
theme, which is about cognitive and perceptual errors in thinking.
We know that the perceptions that people receive are made of the world.
They are easily skewed or they can be easily skewed by social influences as
was the case
in different situations, right?
For example, here I brought you a website and you can check here.
So it gives information about certain type of figures, certain type of pictures where
kind of it skews our view.
They can just go through it and
play around.
And
our minds are not like
blank sheets of paper or recording devices, okay?
Such as cameras or video recorders as some scientists claim, okay?
Instead, our brains construct a picture of the world much as the painters do, for example,
right? Our brains filter our perceptions and fill in missing information based in part on our
expectations, okay?
like we have talked in the previous slides.
And our minds may also distort objects we perceive.
A straight stick when inserted in the water appears to blend, for example, right?
Or we have also a full moon case, right?
Where it appears to be much larger when it's near the horizon, okay?
So this kind of phenomenon
is also called as the moon illusion.
And let's talk about the misperception of random data.
So our brains lose absence of meaning.
And because of this, we may see other or meaningful patterns where there are none of them.
For example, when we look at clouds, when we look at the sky, for example, or see unexplained
lights in the sky, for example, our brains impose meaning on these random shapes we see.
Or when we look at the moon, We may see a face, right?
Or some people may see some other kind of different objects there, right?
So this is also popularly known as the man in the moon.
And because of our brain's inclination to impose meaning on random data, we should maintain
a stance of skepticism
and not jump to conclusions about what we see also.
And the stress as well as
preconceptions about what the world is like can also affect our perception.
So,
for example,
sometimes if we are walking alone
in the dark, right, at night where there is no one, sometimes we may have kind of certain
views, right? Maybe we may see,
maybe based on the shadow, and we may think that there is some person there or
maybe some dog or cat, right?
But later on, we discover that this was just a shadow of some object, for example, right?
And the next point is about the memorable events error, and it involves our ability to vividly
remember outstanding events.
And scientists have discovered channels in our brain
brains that actually hinder most long-term memories by screening out the mundane incidents
in our everyday life.
So just a good example can be that
we may not remember what we ate yesterday or maybe last week.
However, we may remember something that happened 10 years ago because of certain big event,
right? Maybe 10 years ago.
there was a certain incident, maybe there was some
fire going on, or maybe there was an earthquake, or maybe there was an
interesting TV show. Because of that event, we may remember certain
activities which we did at that time,
but we may not remember what we did yesterday or the day before yesterday.
This is called a memorable events error.
And the next point is about the probability error.
So what is the probability that the two people in your class have a birthday on the same month
and day?
So most people guess that the probability is pretty low.
When we miss estimate the probability of an event by a huge margin, we are committing a probability
error. Okay.
And another
close concept for probability error is also a gambler's error.
Okay. So here it means it's a kind of a huge belief that the previous events affect
the probability in a random event.
So sometimes some people
may believe that they have a certain type of
kind of
numbers
that are lucky for them, right?
They may believe that there are some lucky numbers, for example, right?
And so on. Okay, let's continue.
I think it's from this next point, which is about self-serving biases, okay?
And
There are several types of
self-serving biases or errors that kind of impact our thinking and the pursuit of
trust. So it includes misperception that we're in control or tendency to overestimate
ourselves in comparison to others or tendency to exaggerate our strengths and minimize our
weaknesses. So let's talk about them in detail one by one.
So we are predisposed to believe that we are in control of events that are outside of our control.
Okay, so sometimes we may say that I knew, we knew that today there will be rain, right?
And
however, we may say that
based on this, maybe we may try to bring or not to bring an umbrella, right?
And
misperception that we're in control of random events also play out
in superstitious behaviors, right?
Such as wearing out a lucky
shirt during a big game or bringing a good luck charm to an exam, right?
So before the
important event, right?
So some sportsman or maybe some students, right?
Before the exam, right? Before important examinations, they may kind of follow a certain type
of rituals, right? And maybe they may try kind of to wear, maybe certain type of clothing,
or maybe they may do certain type of
activities, or maybe they may kind of talk, tell about a certain type of mantras, or they
may just bring some type of food with them, right, to that event.
So they may think that
this will help them to be in control, right?
So even though
similar activities may increase the person's confidence, right?
And the feeling of that they're in control of the situation, right?
And it may kind of calm them down.
So, however, if we carry the belief that we're in control too far, it can distort
our thinking and lead to poor decisions in our lives, okay?
So, we cannot kind of take this perception, misperception to our everyday activities, right?